真爱
万物都是宇宙的礼物
哈莱姆（纽约黑人居住区） 1987年
我是柯瑞丝·珍·琼斯
My name is Clarence "Precious" Jones.
我希望有个皮肤光滑的男朋友 还有一头漂亮的头发
I wish I had a Light- skinned boyfriend with real nice hair.
我想上杂志的封面
And I wanna be on the cover of a magazine.
但首先我想演一部黑人娱乐台的电影
But first, I wanna be in one of them BET videos.
妈妈说我舞跳得不错
Momma said I can't dance.
但是她说反正也没有人想看我跳舞
Plus, she said, who wants to see my big ass dancing, anyhow?
如果没有自愿的话 那我就点名了
Well, if there are no volunteers, then I'm going to have to call people.
好吧 拉提莎 你是第一个 拉提莎?
Okay, Leticia, you got number one. Leticia!
杰斯 韦斯利 第二个
Jess Wesley, number two.
我喜欢数学 我什么也不说
I Like math. I don't say nothing.
甚至连书也不翻开 就是坐在那儿
I don't open my book, even. I just sit there.
- 来了 - 第六个
- You down? - Number six.
每天我都对自己说 总会发生的
Every day I tell myself something's gonna happen.
我...
I'm... I'm dead serious.
我会突然改变
Like, I'm gonna break through.
或者有人来帮我改变
Or somebody's gonna break through to me.
我会成为正常人
I'm gonna be normal
成为坐在前排 认真听讲的学生
and pay attention, and sit in the front of the class.
座位分配
Distributive principles...
- 迟早有一天 - 原则是...
- Someday. - ...are principles that you can do in your head.
我喜欢威什尔先生
I like Mr. Wisher.
我幻想过他是我丈夫 我们一起住在威彻斯特郡的什么地方
I pretend he my husband and we live someplace Like Westchester.
看着他 他也喜欢我 我知道的
Look at him. He Like me, too, I know it.
从他的眼神里我就能看出来 他总是看着我 冲着我笑
I can tell by his eyes. He always Looking at me and smiling at me.
孩子们!
Boys! Boys! Boys!
- 我他妈才不是你孩子 - 你扰乱课堂秩序了
- I'm not your fucking boy! - You're disrupting the class.
我在讲话 请安静
Yeah, well, I'm talking now, so you listen.
闭上你他妈的臭嘴! 我听不见了!
Shut the fuck up! I'm trying to listen!
威什尔先生知道我会支持他的
Mr. Wisher know I got his back.
122页
One twenty two.
你叫唤什么呢 加兹
Why are we barking, Jess?
我们复习一下周一学的 我想大家都应该完成了
Monday's assignment. I'm assuming everybody did it.
- 没有吗? - 没有
- No? - No.
请安静! 阿珍? 拿上你的东西
Please... Quiet. Precious, get your things.
过来一下
I have... Come here for a second.
又来了
Now this shit.
没做作业的请举手
is there anybody who didn't do their homework?
为什么呢?这可不是请求 是要求 明白吗?
Why? These aren't requests. These are requirements. Okay?
校长办公室叫你
You have to go to the principal's office.
去校长办公室啦!
Go to the principal's office!
够了!
All right, that's enough. That's enough.
不行 不能让他出现在校园里 他在哪?
No, he's not allowed on campus. Where was he seen?
麻烦你能让托克先生从25号房
Could you get Mr. Turk from Room 25,
到16号房去一下吗?谢谢
tell him to go to Room 1 6 right away? Thank you.
不 有人看到他出现在2楼
No. He was seen on the second floor.
好的 谢谢
Yes. Thank you.
叫柯瑞丝进来
Send Clarence in here!
她准备好见你了
She's ready for you now.
泰勒先生 我是莉肯斯汀
Mr. Taylor? Ms. Lichtenstein.
进来
Come in.
马修·威廉姆, 在2楼... 在他更衣室前面
Matthew Williams, second floor.
对 他上周被停课了
in front of his locker. Yes. Suspended last week.
是的
Yeah.
当然 没问题 谢谢
Yes, absolutely. Thank you.
你好 柯瑞丝
Hello, Clarence.
你怀孕了吗?
Are you pregnant?
你才16岁 还是个初中生...
You're 16. You're still in junior high school,
你怀的是你第二个孩子
and you're pregnant with your second child.
我说的没错吧 柯瑞丝?
is that correct, Clarence?
你是不是又怀孕了?
Are you pregnant again?
怎么了 柯瑞丝?
What happened, Clarence?
我做爱了 莉肯斯汀小姐
I had sex, Ms. Lichtenstein.
你有考虑过你现在的处境吗 柯瑞丝?
Do you have any other thoughts about your situation, Clarence?
柯瑞丝?
Clarence?
我有麻烦了么?
Am I in trouble?
谢谢你 我要回去上数学课了
Thank you. I gotta get back to math.
坐下 柯瑞丝! 马上给我坐下!
Sit down, Clarence. Sit down right now.
我们要开个家长见面会 你 我 还有你妈妈
We should have a parent teacher's conference with you, me and your mother.
我妈很忙的
My mother's busy.
行 那我去你家如何?
All right. Well then, how about if I come to your house?
如果我是你 我不会去的
if I were you, I wouldn't.
我... 那我只能让你停课了
I... I'm going to have to suspend you.
不公平 我又没有做错什么!
That ain't fair! I didn't do nothing!
我学的很努力 我的成绩也不差
I do my work! My grades is good!
家里有事请发生了?
is something going on at home?
家里发生了什么事情 我希望你现在马上告诉我!
if something's going on at home, I want you to tell me right now.
你给我弄到烟了吗?
You get my cigarettes?
不 没有 他们没有了
No, they didn't have it.
我捏了一下他给我的烟盒 里面是空的
I played the number, though. I couldn't box it.
哦
Yes. Yeah.
就是这样 爸爸了解你
Right there. Yeah. Daddy loves you.
天哪 阿珍!
Ah Precious
看这里!看这里!
look here, look here
珍小姐 你怎么看这部影片呢?
Precious, what did you think of the film?
我觉得棒极了!
I thought it was fabulous.
- 接下来呢? - 什么?
- What's next for you? - What?
- 感觉如何? - 很棒!
- How are you feeling? - I feel great!
再来一张!再来一张!
Just one more, just one more, quick!
我也爱你们
I love you, too!
我爱你们!
You know I love you!
嗨
Hey, boo!
我啥也不说了!
I ain't gonna say it no more.
出去告诉那些蠢货没事别玩我的门铃
Tell them assholes to stop ringing my bell.
我讨厌那些毒虫
I hate crack heads.
其实除了毒虫没人按她的门铃
No one ever ring this bell except for crack heads.
他们到底想让我们怎么样?
Why they fucking with us?
狗娘养的!别叫唤了!
Stop ringing the goddamn buzzers, motherfuckers!
他们无精打采
Give the ghetto a bad name.
别按门铃了!
Stop ringing the goddamn buzzer!
别按了! 别按了!
Stop it!
按"收听"键 蠢货!
Press "listen," stupid.
我是莉肯斯汀女士 我找柯瑞丝和玛丽·琼斯女士
it's Sandra Lichtenstein for Clarence and Ms. Mary Johnston.
是谁? 阿珍?
Who is that, Precious?
学校里来的
White bitch from school.
你想干吗?
What do you want?
柯瑞丝 我想谈谈你的教育问题.
Clarence, I want to talk to you about your education.
赶走这个贱人!
Eighty- six that bitch.
妈妈不想失去社会补助的钱
My mother don't wanna get cut off welfare.
那是她的重要经济来源
And that's just what this visit gonna result in.
莉肯斯汀小姐 你快走吧! 否则我就揍你一顿!
Ms. Lichtenstein, get out of here before I kick your ass.
好的 柯瑞丝 我和威什尔先生谈过了
All right, Clarence, I spoke to Mr. Wisher,
他说你是他最好的学生之一
and he told me that you're one of his best math students.
如果你个混蛋不把这个贱人赶走
lf your fat ass don't get that bitch away from here...
说你有很大的潜力
...Like a, Like a potential for math.
我也问了麦克奈特女士
So I called Mrs. McKnight
关于更高级的选修课 一对一的教学...
from Higher Education Alternative Each One Teach One.
在特教学校
It's an alternative school.
柯瑞丝 你在听吗?
Clarence, are you listening to me?
我在
Yeah.
好的 麦克奈特老师的"一对一教学"
Okay. Mrs. McKnight. Each One Teach One.
在特瑞萨酒店的11楼 125号大街
it's located at the 11th floor, Hotel Theresa, 125th Street.
- 让那贱人给我滚! - 刚开始不久
- Get rid of that bitch. - The semester started a few days ago,
你不算晚
so you're not too late.
在11楼...
Eleventh floor.
我刚才听明白了!
I heard you the first time.
好的
Okay.
我不知道特教学校是啥 但我想知道
I don't know what an alternative school is, but I feel I wanna know.
我心里感觉很温暖
My heart is all warm inside.
威什尔认为我是个好学生
Mr. Wisher think I'm a good student.
我就知道他喜欢我
I knew that he liked me.
这学校屁用没有
School ain't gonna help none!
猪脑子还是指望扶贫补助吧!
Take your ass down to the welfare.
你他妈的以为她是谁?
Who the fuck she think she is?
我看你觉得自己了不起了 是吧? 自以为是的婊子!
So I guess you think you cute now, right? Uppity bitch.
你他妈的最好闭上你的嘴!
You should have kept your fucking mouth shut.
就因为他让你生了几个孩子
Just 'cause he gonna give you more children than he give me,
你操他妈的就以为你很特殊?
you think you something fucking special?
操你妈 操他妈的!!
Fuck you and fuck him!
阿珍...
Precious!
阿珍!
Precious! Precious!
阿珍 下来! 婊子!
Get down here, bitch!
你让那个白脸老师来家的?
You brought that white bitch up in my house!
你知道不能带那贱人来这!
You... Why would you bring that bitch up in here?
不是我让她来的
I didn't bring her here.
那操她的按什么门铃?
Well, why the fuck did she ring my buzzer?
你说得我都听到了 阿珍
I can't hear you, Precious.
要不是因为你他妈的大臭嘴
Since you got so much motherfucking mouth,
把那个贱人带到我家里来
and you gonna bring a bitch up in my house,
她怎么会他妈的按我的门铃?
why would that bitch ring my goddamn buzzer?
我没让她来!
I didn't tell her to come here.
我觉得你现在可能觉得自己是个女人了
See, I think right now, you feeling like you're becoming a grown woman.
就凭你在厨房做的那堆屎
Cause of that shit you pulled in the kitchen.
我就应该操死你! 但我给你个机会
I should've fucked you up, but I let you walk away,
让你自己看着办
and I let you come get yourself together.
但是 婊子 我跟你说清楚 你要是再敢做这屎事
But, bitch, I'm gonna let you know if you ever pull that shit on me again,
那就是你他妈的死无超生之日
that will be your last motherfucking day standing,
我说到做到
I promise you that.
你让那个操他妈的白人婊子来按门铃
You gonna send a white bitch to my motherfucking buzzer?
说什么高等教育?
Talking about some higher education?
你就是个猪脑子婊子!你永远连屁都学不会
You're a dummy, bitch, you will never know shit.
没人会要你
Don't nobody want you. Don't nobody need you.
还想他妈的操来操去 操我的男人?
You done fucked around and fucked my motherfucking man
操他妈的 生两个小孩?
and had two motherfucking children,
其中一个他妈的是个欠操野兽
and one of them is a goddamn animal,
疯子一样他妈的跑来跑去!
running around, looking crazy as a motherfucker.
婊子 你知道不? 我觉得你在搞我
Bitch, you know what? See, I think you... I think you're trying me.
你真的他妈的想搞我 你搞光了我的钱
I think you're really trying to fuck with me. You're fucking with my money.
又站在那儿 向下看着我
And you're gonna stand up there and look down at me
操他妈的 真以为自己是个女人了
like you're a motherfucking woman.
我让你看看 啥叫真正的女人!
I'm gonna show you what real women do, bitch.
他妈的 你还不知道真正女人能干啥
See, you don't know what real motherfucking women do.
他妈的 真正的女人会牺牲
Real motherfucking women sacrifice.
他妈的 我早该打掉你那个欠操的孩子
I should've aborted your motherfucking ass. Cause you ain't shit.
因为你屁都不是 怀上你的那天我就知道
I knew it the day the doctors put you in my goddamn hand
你就个天杀的东西!
you wasn't a goddamn thing,
你脸上还挂着笑?
and you have that smirk on your face, bitch?
去他妈的!
Get it off your fucking face!
接着笑啊! 笑给我看啊 肥婊子
Now smile about that! Smile about that, you fat bitch.
我弄死你! 婊子
I'm gonna kill you, bitch!
跑? 你这个婊子
Get off me, bitch!
你真的需要好好休息一下了
You really need to get some rest.
明天是那么重要的日子
You have such a big day ahead of you tomorrow.
记住 妈妈爱你
And remember, Mommy loves you.
阿珍... 你知道我深爱着你
Precious, you know I love you.
我已经把我家里那个白女人扫地出门了!
I'm gonna kick that white lady out of my house,
搬来和我住吧
move you in with me.
我们一起住在威彻斯特郡
Wanna live in Westchester?
你要去哪? 你要去哪?
Where you going?
记得去一下852号拿我的烟
Make sure you play my 852 and tell them to box it.
顺便拿点糖回来
And get some kitty litter.
艾瑟 你在哪呢?
Ethel, where you at?
阿珍 我们去哪玩?
Precious, what are we gonna play?
一边玩去 小鬼!
Girl, get the fuck out of here.
你自己不用去学校吗?
Ain't you supposed to be at school or something?
你说要和我一起玩的
You said we was gonna play.
这就是我不跟你玩的原因
That's exactly why we ain't gonna be playing.
我从没说过那话
I never said nothing like that.
# 你曾听过梦说话么?我有哦
# 你曾经被梦吓到过吗? 说着"你愿意嫁给我么?"
# 是那么的堂皇 实在太...太神圣
# 你见过梦跳舞吗?我有哦
# 你可曾见天堂就在你怀抱中
# 说着 我爱你 我愿意
# 好吧 那个会走路会说话的梦
# 还有在我怀抱中的天堂 就是你
你总是跟我扯这些没用的 你自己也没当真
You would say some shit like that to me, and you don't even mean it?
不!我没有玩你 不 如果她来的话 等等
No, I'm not playing with you. No, and she call... Hold on.
你好 这里是"一对一教学"
Each One Teach One, hold, please.
对 她给我打过电话了 我知道肯定不止这样 特蕾
Yes. She called my house. I know it wasn't your sister, Trey.
因为那不是她
Because it wasn't her.
这里就是喽?
What this is here?
"一对一教学"
Each One Teach One.
我来找特教学校
I'm looking for an alternative school.
就这里了
This is an alternative.
怎么个特教法?
What alternative is?
你到底想问啥?
What exactly are you asking me?
我学校的老师让我来这
Lady at my other school told me to come here.
特瑞沙旅馆 上面有个特教学校
Hotel Theresa. Said it's an alternative school.
特教学校就像一个选择 换种做事方式
An alternative school, it's like a choice. it's a different way of doing things.
所以我需要一些开除证明 证明你被开除了
So, I need your discharge papers saying that they discharged you.
我被学校踹了 因为我怀孕了
I got kicked out of school cause I was pregnant.
但是我还是需要开除证明 否则我不能让你来的
Well, I still need your discharge papers, otherwise we can't let you in.
莉肯斯汀女士没说过要证明的
Ms. Lichtenstein didn't say all that.
你好像是她点过名的
You the one she called about.
柯瑞丝 珍 琼斯?
Clarence P. Jones?
你的开除证明和相关资料都已经送过来了
They already sent over your discharge papers and stuff.
我今天就开始上课吗?
I could start today?
对的 你现在接受过救助没?
Yeah. Are you currently receiving AFDC?
我妈妈帮我和我女儿取助贫款
My mother get AFDC for me and my daughter.
所以你和你女儿在你妈妈名下 你们用的她的预算?
So your mother has custody of you and your daughter, and you're on her budget?
好的 我需要你妈妈的一份收入证明
Okay, well, I'm gonna need a copy of your mother's budget,
还有电话和详细地址
and a copy of your phone bill and your utility bill.
我现在要给你做一份测试 测试一下你的阅读能力和数学水平
We gotta give you a few tests, test your reading and your math level,
检测一下的水平 决定谁来教你
see where to place you.
稍等 亲爱的 一对一教学 你好 请稍等
Hold on, baby. Each One Teach One, hold.
你想要参加高中课程 必须至少拿到8分以上
To enter into the GED classes, you gotta get an 8.0 or better on the TABE.
天空布满了乌云 一片昏暗...
快乐的
这些考试里总有些问题
There's always something wrong with these tests.
这些考试让我看起来像傻子一样
These tests paint a picture of me with no brain.
让我觉得我母亲
These tests paint a picture of me and my mother,
我的家庭看起来都傻而无知
my whole family, as less than dumb.
成为了被拒之一旁的丑陋的黑人 无工作可找
Just ugly, black grease to be wiped away, find another job for.
有时候我希望自己死了算了
Sometimes I wish I was dead.
我觉得我会没事的 因为我总是向前看
I'll be okay, I guess, cause I'm Looking up.
看看从楼上摔下来的钢琴
I'm Looking up for a piano to fall.
书桌 沙发 电视机... 说不定还有我妈
Or a desk, couch, TV... Momma, maybe.
总是挡着我的路
always something in my way.
这么贵
Yeah, man.
- 能给个优惠么 - 好吧伙计
Oyo, make sure you get that for me, too, man.
特教
Alternative.
他妈的 别抽烟
Man, you gotta stop smoking them shits, man.
做这种买卖会出事的 伙计
That ain't the only thing that's gonna fucking kill you.
在大街上扒手会要你命的
Hustling in these streets gonna kill you.
该做还要做
it is what it is.
我的思绪又回到了现实
Then my mind come back down to Earth.
你穿的可真"美丽动人" 大海怪
Let me get some of that sweet ass, orca!
嗨 大妈?
What up, mama?
这些男孩总是嘲笑我
Why boys always grabbing on themselves?
你他妈刚才说啥? 想找事吗?
You heard what the fuck I said? I said give me some fucking ass.
我没开玩笑 我听到了!
I'm serious! When you gonna let me hit that?
她刚才笑咱们
That bitch is laughing...
我希望他们别来惹我
I wish they'd leave me alone.
看她那傻样!
- She's stupid. - Yeah.
真差劲
Yo, that's not even funny.
她怎么都是一坨屎
That's what she'd get anyway, no.
阿珍!
Precious!
妈! 给我点钱!
Ma, I need some money!
妈 我饿了
Ma, I'm hungry!
过来照顾照顾你妈妈 阿珍
Come take care of Mommy, Precious.
什么时候才能结束这狗屁
I wish she'd stop this shit.
有一天我哭了
The other day I cried.
我觉得自己很傻 但是你知道吗?
I felt stupid. But you know what?
操那一天
Fuck that day.
这可能就是上帝 或者管它什么 创造新的一天的原因
That's why God, or whoever, makes new days.
但还是饿啊
Still hungry, though.
你想让我抛弃我的孩子?
Nigger wants me to leave my kids.
你就是我的孩子
They're my kids.
- 你想吃点啥 亲爱的 - 给我来个外带桶好不
- What didn't you want, baby? - Give me a basket, please.
- 多大的 - 我不知道 我还在想呢 你看着来吧
- Sides? - I don't know yet. Still thinking about it. Trying to watch my figure.
巴奇 来个十块儿装的
Butchie, you got a 10 piece ready?
再来一份土豆沙拉
Potato salad.
谢谢
Thank you.
她还真敢
Hell, no, she didn't!
抓住她 抓住那个肥婊子
Get her ass! Get that big bitch!
不 我才不是
No, I am not the one.
你是成人启蒙班(A.B.E.)的?
You in ABE?
是的
Yeah.
时间不等人
Time's a wasting.
你叫什么名字?
What's your name?
柯瑞丝
Clarence.
你要进来吗?
Are you coming in?
20秒后关门
That door closes in 20 seconds.
今天大家怎么样?
How are you guys doing today?
你要加入我们吗? 坎翠拉?
Would you like to join us, Consuelo?
坎翠拉 很高兴你能来
Consuelo, class is beginning.
你们知道你们上的是成人启蒙班
You guys know that you are in the ABE class.
这不是正式课程 是让你们为正式课程做准备
This is not GED. This is to get you ready for your GED.
笔记本在这个课程中非常重要 不要忘了
These journals are very important to this class, so do not forget them.
每天在这儿都要用到
You will need to use them every day that you are here.
是上课的关键
They are the key to this class.
乔安 你又迟到了 已经9:07了
it's 9:07, Joann. You're late.
你不知道早饭是很重要的吗?
You're the one who said breakfast is the most important meal of the day.
明天9点就关门
Tomorrow, that door will be locked at 9:00.
我想让你们介绍一下自己 你的名字 生日
I want you to state your name, where you were born,
最喜欢的颜色 你擅长什么? 你为什么会来这里
your favorite color, something you do well and why you're here.
我先来
I'll go first.
你啥时候来的?
When you due?
- 我的名字是... - 算了吧 你不知道
- My name... - What you mean, you don't know?
蓝·雨 这是你真名?
...is Blue Rain.
- 是的 没错 - 那你大名叫 蓝?
- That's your real name? - Yes, it is. Your first name's Blue?
我最喜欢的颜色是紫色 我唱歌唱得不错
My favorite color is purple. I sing well.
我来这儿...
And I'm here
因为我喜欢教学
because I love to teach.
她爱唱
She like to sing.
兰达
Rhonda?
我希望我也能唱 去教堂里的唱诗班
I wish I could sing. Go to church and sing in the choir.
表现一下
Show them how it's done.
(兰达的口音非常重) 好吧 我名字叫兰达·帕切丝·约翰森
All right. My name is Rhonda Patrice Johnson.
有问题?
Problem?
- 真欠扇 - 啥?
- I should smack her. - What?
我出生于金斯顿 嘉米卡 我最喜欢的颜色是蓝色
I was born in Kingston, Jamaica, and my favorite color is blue.
饭做得不错
And I cook good.
我妈妈曾在第七大街有一家餐厅
My mother, she used to have a restaurant over on 7th Avenue.
在她生病之前 我都是跟她学东西
Before she get sick, she teach me everything.
我来是为了提高阅读水平 让我能上正式课程
So I'm here to get my reading up, so I can get my GED.
我叫丽塔·罗密欧 我是哈勒姆本地人
My name is Rita Romero. I was born here in Harlem.
我来这儿因为我有瘾 所以退学了
I'm here 'cause I was an addict and I dropped out of school.
所以我从没学过读书和写东西
So I never got my reading and writing together.
我最爱黑色
My favorite color's black.
你擅长什么?
What do you do good?
恩 乔安 你擅长什么?
"Well," Joann. "What do you do well?"
- 我擅长什么? - 不是
- What do I do well? - NO
- 丽塔 - 我是个好母亲 非常好的母亲
- Rita? - I'm a good mother. Very good mother.
我的名字叫佳梅 我最喜欢的颜色是红色...
My name's Jermaine. My favorite color is red.
告诉我们出生地先
- Tell us where you were born first.
我出生于布朗克斯 还住在这儿
I was born in the Bronx. Still live there.
我最喜欢红色 曾经是蓝色
My favorite color is red. Used to be blue.
我舞跳的不错
I can dance real good.
我一个朋友介绍我来"一对一教学" 所以...
Homie of mine told me about Each One Teach One,
我来这躲麻烦
so I came here to stay out of trouble.
所以你来哈勒姆来躲避麻烦? 就这些?
So you came here to Harlem to stay out of trouble? is that right?
是的
Yeah.
- 坎翠拉? - 这是扯淡
- Consuelo? - This is bullshit.
你这么认为?
You think so?
柯瑞丝?
Clarence?
我可以不说吗?
Can I skip, too?
乔安?
Joann?
好的 我叫乔安 大家好
Okay. I'm Joann. Hey.
我最喜欢的颜色是荧光黄!
My favorite color is fluorescent beige
我的野心是录制自己的唱片
and my ambition is to have my own record layer.
- 什么唱片 - 姐们 你从哪来的
What's a record layer?
到这个学校来干嘛?
Tell us where you come from and why you come to this school.
我出生在国王县医院
I was born in Kings County Hospital,
9岁的时候 我妈带我搬到哈勒姆
but my mother moved us to Harlem when I was nine.
我来这儿是为了上正式课程 然后...
I'm here to get my GED, and then...
反正我已经入了音乐行业了
Well, I'm already into the music industry.
我只是来受点教育什么的 让我继续提高
I'm just trying to take care of this little education thing so I can move up.
我们上课吧 这里是成人启蒙班课程
Let's begin. This is ABE.
我能说几句吗?
Can I go?
我希望我还坐在教室的后排
I wish I could sit in the back of the class again.
我的名字是柯瑞丝 珍 琼斯
My name Clarence "Precious" Jones.
可以叫我阿珍
I go by Precious.
我住在哈勒姆 我喜欢黄色
I live in Harlem. I like yellow.
还有... 我在之前的学校里有些麻烦 所以我来到这...
And I had problems at my other school, so I come here.
你擅长什么?
Something you do well?
什么也没
Nothing.
每个人总有自己擅长的东西
Everybody's good at something.
来吗
Come on.
我会做饭 还有...
Well, I can cook. And...
我从没有上课说话过
I never really talked in class before.
那让你感觉如何呢?
How does that make you feel?
就这儿
Here.
让我感觉到现在这样
it makes me feel here.
大家请打开笔记本
Everybody open their journal.
在第一页上方写上日期 然后写
Write the date at the top of the page, and write.
我不介意你们全都拼错
I don't care if you spell everything wrong.
我不介意语法正不正确
I don't care if it's grammatically incorrect. But just write.
只管写 写下你们所有的感受
Write anything that you're feeling.
这门课程就像个旋转门
This class will be a revolving door.
你们有人会通过 有的人不会
Some of you will make it and some of you won't.
15分钟时间 开始
Fifteen minutes. Go.
以前... 我英语课得过A- 什么话都不用说
Before, I got a A- minus at English, and I didn't have to say nothing.
雨小姐说她会天天看我们本子上写的东西
Ms. Rain said we gonna read and write in our notebooks every day.
她做这干什么?
How we supposed to do that?
然后她说 她看到了我脸上的担忧
But then she see the worry on my face and she say,
万事开头难
"The Longest journey begin with a single step."
管她妈的啥意思
Whatever the fuck that's supposed to mean.
拜托 做点花样 你会喜欢的
Come on, come on, do the work.
学会它
You love it, love it, learn it.
坎翠拉?
Consuelo?
坎翠拉 你的 "C"
"C" for Consuelo.
踹（Kick）你一脚的"C"
"C" for kick your ass.
踹你一脚是"K" 傻冒
it's "K" for kick your ass, stupid.
"D"是我的 雨小姐
I got the "D," Ms. Rain.
好的 我们看看会是什么
gook we fuck see this
"屌"的"D"
"D" for dick.
那谁叫我贱人的时候 显然是不了解我
Ms. Rain, tell this little ass bitch that she don't know me.
你可不是么
Which you wish you had.
- 来帮帮她 - "E"
- Help her. - "E."
"E."
E...
肥婆的"F"
"F" for fat.
什么
What?
不错
Good.
操 怎么了
Hey! Hey! Hey! Quit it! Hey!
- 什么? - 嘿!你们!停下!
- What? - Hey, you stop it right now!
- 操 - 去你妈的
- You fucking... - Quit it!
- 她打我 - 闭嘴!
- She just hit me! - Drop it!
贱人!
Shut the fuck up!
她扇我!
She just slapped me!
出去
Get out.
在我课上不准打架 坐下
We don't fight in my class. Sit down.
残障的"C"
"C" for cold.
你和谁一起住?
Do you live with anybody?
- 和我妈妈 - 她是干什么的?
- My mother. - What does she do?
什么也不干
She don't do nothing.
我想让你读一下这本书的这一页
I want you to read a page from this book.
试试看
Try.
你只需要念出来就可以了
All I need you to do is sound out these words for me.
你不用每个词都认识
You don't have to know every word.
试试看 别害怕 或者... 试试看 不用怕磕磕绊绊的
You just have to... it doesn't matter if you stumble or... Try for me...
你只需要... 说你认识的词
...or trip up on it. You just need to say what you know.
你可以的 试试看 一个词一个词的来
Come on. You can do this. Try. Take it word by word.
- 你听明白我说的了么? - 阿珍!
- Are you listening to me? - Precious!
我就是想了解一下... 你阅读的水平
I just wanna know where you are in your reading skills.
我需要了解一下的测试情况...
Cause I'm looking at your test scores...
高等教育?! 你个傻逼婊子!
Some higher fucking learning. You're a dumb bitch!
试一下 试一下?
Try to read, okay?
你比你妈还要强
I want you better than your mother.
- 我叫个护士来 - 不要
- I'm gonna call the nurse. - No.
我看起来都一样
it all look the same to me.
这是什么?
What's this?
我做不来 雨小姐
I can't do that, Ms. Rain.
加把劲
Push yourself.
"A"
A
那这个词呢?
What's this word?
"海岸边的一天"
字母你认识吗? 试试看
Do you know the letters? Come on.
D
"D"
A
"A"
Y
"Y"
你认识这个词吗?
Do you know that word?
天
"Day"
这个词呢?
What word is that?
A... T...
"At" "At"
不错 差不多了 这个词是"在"
Good. Almost. The word is "At."
在
"At"
那
"The"
大声读出来
Sound it out.
贱人
"Beach."(bitch)
这个音短一些 和婊子差不多
The word is "Shore." it's almost like "Beach."
很不错
Very good.
现在整个句子读一遍
Now, read the whole thing for me.
一...
"A
天...
"Day
在...
"At The
短一些
"Shore."
带着你的肥腚过来
Get your big ass in here.
你今天早上去哪了
Where was you at this morning?
我在和你说话 你今天早上去哪了?
You hear me talking to you? Where was you at this morning?
学校 我去学校了
School. I was at school.
- 你在说谎 - 不 我没有 - 你就是
- You a lying whore. - I'm not lying. - You is.
社会保障打电话来说要降低保障金
The welfare done called here saying they gonna remove you from my budget
因为本来应该去学校的
'cause you ain't been attending school regularly.
我说过我被开除了 我已经在家待了2周了
I told you I got kicked out. I been home nearly every day for two weeks now.
你今天没和我说什么学校
You ain't told me nothing about no damn school today.
我早上告诉过你我去学校了
I told you I was going to school this morning.
你最好去往锅里放点东西
You plan on putting some food in that frying pan?
阿珍 你有啥要说吗?
Precious, you got something you wanna say?
- 没有 - 那就别摔得那么响 明白?
- No. - Then don't be slamming shit down in here. You understand?
遵命
Yes, ma'am.
你就应该忘掉那些狗屁学校...
You need to forget about that school shit and
省下社会救助金
take your ass down to the welfare.
- 我在学校学知识 - 知识是个屁?
- I'm getting a stipend from school. - Fool, what the fuck is a stipend? What is that?
操那有啥用! 我说了让你去申请社会保障!
Fuck a stipend. I said take your ass down to the welfare.
现在?
Right now?
现在他妈的有啥用?
Why in the fuck would you go right now?
天都黑了 屁早关门了
it's at nighttime. Shit is closed. You gotta be there by 7:00 a.m.
你要是想找到人说话 你得早上7点去
in the morning if you wanna talk to somebody.
蠢得要死
Fucking stupid.
你觉得自己很了不起是不是? 是这么回事吧
You think you're too good now? is that what it is?
你觉得社会保障金你看不起?
You think you is too good for the welfare?
白人申请社会保障金的 比黑人多了去了
There's more white folk getting assistance than it is niggers, Ms. Onassis.
我是想说...
I think I said the rapy...
你速度点! 我他妈的快饿死了!
Hurry your ass up. I am in here fucking starving.
如果我饿死了 你能去哪?
Now what you gonna do if I die of starvation? Where you gonna go after that?
哦对! 我忘了! 学校!
I forgot. School.
那人说啥来着?那个叫啥?一对啥?一对一教学
Each... What that bitch say? Each one do what? Each one teach one?
管他们操他妈的教啥
Well, they don't know who the fuck they teaching,
反正你屁都学不会
cause you can't learn shit.
别听那些白人的
Keep on listening to them white people.
到最后还是被操
That's what's gonna get you fucked up.
阿珍 我饿了
Precious, I'm hungry.
你没他妈的把豆子和那个猪蹄放一起?
You ain't cooked no collard greens with the fucking pigs' feet?
没有点粮食我怎么吃猪蹄?
Like, how am I supposed to eat pigs' feet with no collard greens?
而且这猪蹄上他妈的怎么那么多毛?!
And why in the fuck does that pigs' feet have so much hair in it?
你吃给我看看 你吃这堆狗屎
You eat it. You come eat this shit.
- 我不饿 - 你就是饿了
- I'm not hungry, though. - Yes, you is.
阿珍 如果你天杀的不吃的话...
Precious, if you don't get this goddamn plate...
吃完了去给我做 再做坏了 你就继续吃!
You just fix mine when you get done. Since you fucked it up, you gonna eat it up.
给我速度点 阿珍 我她妈也饿着呢
Hurry up and eat, Precious. I'm fucking hungry, too.
而且别等它凉了 因为凉了的猪蹄恶心的要死
And don't let it get cold, cause cold ass pigs' feet is nasty as shit.
你吃什么?
我不饿
吃吧!吃吧!
妈妈...
快坐下你的肥腚吧
好好吃吧 马上就凉了
可能你不明白 我真的不饿
吃吧 贱人
妈妈
说说你家里的情况
So, tell me about... Tell me about your home life.
没啥好说的
Ain't nothing to really talk about.
这里很安全 只管说吧
You're in a safe place. Just talk. What's going on?
到底怎么了 一提到家
What's the first thing that comes to your mind
你首先想到什么
when you think about home?
我想有自己的电视 可以在自己房间里看
I just wish I had my own TV, so I could watch it in my room.
不用和我妈一起看
lf I had my own TV, I wouldn't have to watch it with my mother.
和你妈妈一起看电视会怎么样呢?
And what's it like, watching TV with your mother?
你和你妈妈一起看过电视吗?
You enjoy watching TV with your mother?
我需要了解你的家庭状况 我需要了解你生活的状况
I need to know about your home life. I need to know what it's like where you live.
我妈就像一头坐在沙发上的鲸鱼
My mother's like a whale on the couch.
她说我整天就知道吃 但是她老是逼着我吃
She say I eat all the time, but she always making me eat.
所以她说我肥得一塌糊涂
Then she call me a fat mess.
她说因为我房子显得小
She say the apartment is little 'cause of me.
有时候她去玩六合彩
Only time she ever leaves is to play her numbers.
那时我感觉自己也天天坐在屋子里
I feel like I could just sit in the house with her every day,
像坨屎
the shades drawn,
看电视 吃东西 再看电视 再吃东西
watch TV, eat, watch TV, eat again.
又能怎样?
Can you help out with that?
我们说说别的?
Can we talk about something else now?
说说你第一个孩子
How about your firstborn?
小芒果?
Mongo?
小芒果? 是...
Mongo is her... is that...
小芒果 曼格罗伊的简称
Mongo. That's short for "mongoloid."
你就这么叫她?还是这是个昵称?
is that what you call her? Or that's... What is that? A nickname?
有时候她也到家来
She got Down's syndrome.
你好吗?阿珍
How you doing, Precious?
图茜奶奶有时候带小芒果回家
My grandmother Toosie bring Little Mongo over to our house
社会救助人员来的时候 假装她和我们一起住
on days when the social worker come, so it look like she live with us.
去看看!操你妈傻了!
Answer the fucking door.
看看你都干了些啥? 操你妈的!
Do you see what you did? God damn it.
然后我妈妈就拿到了钱 还有一些给我和小芒果的吃的
Then my mother gets money and the food stamps for me and Mongo.
谁?
Who is it?
我是特纳
it's Ms. Turner.
社工来了
Social worker's here.
怎么不他妈的告诉我那贱人这么早就来了?!
Why didn't you tell me that bitch was coming so fucking early?
操 假发!快把假发拿来
My fucking wig. Come get my wig!
上来吧!
Come up!
我的口红呢?
Where's my lipstick?
谢谢 谢谢
Thank you, thank you.
- 别乱动我! - 别拿孩子出气
- Get off of me. - Leave that child alone, please.
管好你自己的事
Mind your goddamn business.
- 嗨 阿珍 - 嗨
- Hi, Precious. - Hey.
- 你好 特纳小姐 你最近怎么样 - 嗨 玛丽 你好吗?
- Hello, Ms. Turner. How you doing? - Hi, Mary. How are you?
还不错 我的可爱小孙女把这儿弄得一团糟
Please excuse that. My sweet grandbaby just knocked it over.
快请坐 挺乱的 别介意
Please, have a seat. Excuse the mess.
- 谢谢 - 谢谢
- Thank you. - Thanks.
你最近好吗?玛丽
How are you, Mary?
我很不错 特纳小姐 谢谢你
I'm doing really good, Ms. Turner. Thank you.
你上次带孩子去医生那是什么时候了?
When was the last time you've taken her to the doctor?
阿珍?我们什么时候带孩子去的来着
Precious, when... When did we take her? The baby?
- 上个月 - 哦对 16号 16号 对的对的 是的
- Last month. - Yeah... On the 16th. On the 16th. Yes, yes, ma'am.
好的 医生怎么说?
Okay, and what did the doctor say?
医生说进展很顺利
They said that she's progressing really good.
一切都很好
She's doing really good.
- 那很不错 - 是啊 呵呵
- That's good. - Yes, ma'am.
你有试着找工作了么?
And have you been looking for a job?
我找过 特纳小姐 但是他们总是说同样的话
I have, Ms. Turner. I am. But they've all been saying the same thing.
你知道 他们总是说再联系 就再没找过我
You know, they'll call me back. They'll get back to me.
你什么时候去找的工作?
When did you go looking for the job?
上个礼拜去过..然后...
I went last week and I filled out several applications.
我申请了几个 但是还是得到同样的答复 说他们会打电话给我
And they all said the same thing, that they would call me.
好的 妈妈
Mommy!
啊 啊
No! No!
那是新微波炉么?
is that a new microwave oven?
微波炉? 恩
A... A microwave?
不 我们都在炉子上热东西
No, ma'am. We warm our things up in the oven.
- 我那可能是烤面包机 - 是的 是的 女士
- I see. it's a toaster oven. - Yes. Yes, ma'am.
好的 我改天再来和你聊聊...
Okay. I will be seeing and speaking with you
大约一周之内吧.
in a week or so.
- 一周之内? - 是的
- in a week or so? - Yes.
好吧 能告诉我大概什么时间您来么?
Okay, do you know what time you'll be... You'll be coming?
- 我会通知你的 - 好的
- I'll let you know. - Okay.
- 我会让你知道的 - 非常感谢
- I'll let you know. - Thank you so much.
- 阿珍 有什么要问我的吗? - 嗯
- Precious, any questions for me? - En En
阿珍 你最近怎么样?
How are you, Precious?
- 还不错你呢? - 我也不错 谢谢
- I'm doing good. How you doing? - I'm good, thank you.
女士们 打扰你们了
Ladies, thank you for your time.
非常感谢 特纳小姐... 祝你今天愉快
Thank you so much, Ms. Turner. Have a great day.
- 你也是 再见 希拉 - 再见
- And you. Bye, Sheila. - Bye.
过来把这操他妈的孩子弄走! 拿走!
Come get this motherfucking... Get her.
我和那贱人谈话的时候 动过来动过去
Moving all around and shit while I'm trying to talk to this bitch.
搞得我浑身痒痒!
Makes me fucking itch.
糖就那么扔地上了 操她的猪脑袋
She done threw her fucking candy on the floor.
该死的
Goddamn animal.
你要给她糖?放回地上去!
And now you gonna give it to her? Put the fucking candy back on the floor!
你就这么捡起来给她?
Then you go and pick it up and let her have it.
你真她妈的傻! 你们娘俩一样傻!
You're so fucking stupid. Just like her dumb ass.
那个贱人一来 我她妈的装模作样!
That bitch gonna come up in here and I gotta fucking make pretend?
烦得要死!
I'm so sick of it.
我不知道你她妈的摇啥头!
I don't know what the fuck you shaking your head for.
换你也好不到哪去!
You didn't do no goddamn better.
我们来谈谈你的爸爸吧
You know what? Let's talk about your father.
跟我谈谈你和他的关系是怎样的
Tell me about your relationship with him.
我也不比你知道得多多少 怀特小姐
I don't know much more than you do, Ms. White.
是怀斯小姐
it's Ms. Weiss.
那就就你所知 谈谈你爸爸吧
Talk to me about the little you do know about your father,
不管你知不知道 这是很重要的
cause it is important, whether you know it or not.
他使我怀上了那个孩子 之前的那个
He give me this baby and my one before it, but I...
你说他使你怎么样了?
What did you say he gave you?
- 没啥 - 不 我听见了
- Nothing. - No, Clarence, you just said
- 你刚说你爸爸使你怎么样了 - 没有...
- your father gave you something.
- 我听到你说了 - 你屁都没听到
- I heard you just say... - You didn't hear shit.
- 我听到你说 你爸... - 我屁都没说...
- I heard you say your father... - I ain't say nothing. I ain't say shit like it.
- 我不在乎 - 我啥都没有说
- I don't care, honey. - I didn't say nothing like that.
我必须了解这个 我们继续吧
I need to know this. Let's move on.
我需要了解才能帮助你...
I need to know this to help you.
- 我们不能换个话题么 - 那好吧
- Bitch, can we change the subject? - Okay.
那我们下次见吧 或许我见个别的什么人
Well, I'll see you next time, then. Or maybe you'll see someone else.
不过如果你想把支票拿到手的话
But you're gonna have to talk to somebody
你总要跟什么人讲出来 宝贝儿
if you want your check, sweetie.
我觉得他们就像吸血鬼
I see vampires, too.
他们深夜才来 他们说我也是他们的一员
They come at night. They tell me I'm one of them.
他们说 "阿珍 你是属于我们的"
They say, "Precious, you belong with us."
然后他们到楼上去
And then they go downstairs through the floor.
住我们楼下的 也是吸血鬼
The people that live under us, they is vampires,
我知道肯定没错
so that's where they should go.
他们真的很恶心
They be so nasty, though,
到处脏掉的卫生棉条 在垃圾堆里面大便
leaving their dirty tampons and shit in the garbage.
根本都懒得清理下
Don't even offer to take it out.
他们才没有任何家庭教养
They got no fucking home training.
我也去看过医生了 挺好的
I been going to the doctor, too. it's nice.
雨小姐要是知道我第一次生孩子没有
Ms. Rain fall out when she found out
去看过医生的话 肯定吓坏的
I ain't never been to no doctor before.
她不知道我怎么把第一个孩子生在厨房地板上
Don't know how I had my first baby on the kitchen floor
我妈还在后面踢我屁股
with my momma kicking me upside my head.
还记得你一开始说的
Them the kind of things you're talking about
一提到家我首先想到什么吗?
when you say, say whatever come to my mind?
就是这样 再见了 社会保障金
That's the end of them welfare checks.
我就是再也不想撒谎了 那些事我一句都不该说
I just couldn't Lie no more. I shouldn't have said none of that.
妈妈肯定会杀了我的
Momma gonna kill me.
真该死
Motherfuckers!
我们来这儿干吗?
Are we done?
我们今天不这么做
I'm not doing this with you today.
有一晚 我们出去玩了
At night, we went out on a field trip.
这些姑娘们都快疯了
These girls is crazy.
之前从来没有人像这样握着我的手
Ain't nobody ever grabbed my hand like that before.
我要把这一切都教给我的宝贝
I'm gonna teach my baby all of this.
不用害怕 那时鬼扯 那是鬼扯
No fear. That's bullshit. That's bullshit. You mean, write a whole new one?
不 姑娘 还用我跟你解释么?
No, girl, if I need to explain myself to you...
- 你要搞明白 - 因为我蠢么?
- You'll figure it out. - You think that I'm stupid?
哦 天啊 我是不是应该相信你?
Oh, my God. That I believe in you?
我是不是应该觉得你很有才?
That I think you're incredible?
是 不过我也不知道为什么
Yes, but I don't know what to do.
好了 下一个是谁?
All right, pull it together. Okay. Who's next?
我很高兴能在这里
I'm happy to be writing.
- 来 上台吧 - 我很开心能在这个学校
- Go ahead, Rhonda. - I'm happy to be in school, too.
雨小姐说我们要把每天的事都写给她
Ms. Rain say we gonna write every day in our notebook.
她也会每天给我们写回复
She gonna write back to us every day, too.
昨天是我来到这个国家之后第一次去教堂
Yesterday I went to church for the first time since I come to this country.
我穿过了布鲁克林
l got all the way to Brooklyn.
教堂就坐落在33号大街的角落里
The church was up the block and around the corner upon the 33 train.
牧师布道了2小时30分 我很感动
The preacher preached two and a half hours
兰达 兰达
about Jehovah. Rhonda! Rhonda!
圣主 圣子 救世主
"And how Lord Jesus, Son of God, Messiah, Jehovah delivers."
等一下 等一下! 这是个童话故事么?
is that a fairytale?
请坐吧
Sit down. Did anybody do this assignment?
妈妈说这个学校屁也不是
Momma say this school ain't shit.
她说你只写笔记什么也学不会
She say you can't learn nothing writing in no book.
- 这点她说错了 - 这是一个童话故事... 我在学习
- This is a fairytale called "Enchanted." - She wrong about that. I is learning.
很久很久以前 在一个很遥远的地方
Once upon a time, in a faraway land,
有一个漂亮的公主 叫做乔安...
there lived a beautiful princess named Joanna.
她非常非常俊俏 而且又高又苗条
She was very, very fly and extra, extra tall,
每一个男人都喜欢她 无论大小
and every single boy loved her, big and small.
除了一个白痴智障的蠢男人
Except for one idiot boy who was so stupid and dumb.
但比较所有喜欢她的男人 他却是长得最帅的一个
And out of all the cute boys who loved her, he was the cutest one.
- 我现在只写了这么多 - 很不错的开头 很不错的开篇吗
- That's all I got so far. - That's a good beginning.
我也经常想起小芒果 谢谢
Thinking about Little Mongo, too. I miss her.
我想念她 写一个童话故事的话...
That's how you start a fairytale.
我马上就要生一个新宝宝了
I'm happy my baby coming up.
我也会把这个读给我的宝宝 在他的房间画满色彩
I'm gonna read to this baby, too, and hang colors on its wall.
听好了 宝贝 妈妈不傻 妈妈爱你 听
Listen, baby. Mother not dumb. Mother Love you. Listen.
很久很久以前 有一个会魔法的公主
Once upon a time, there was a magical princess
生活在漂浮在海上的魔法泡泡里面
who lived in a magical bubble under the sea.
但她来自地面...
And she was from land.
别尖叫了
Stop screaming.
他的名字阿杜·佳梅尔·路易斯·琼斯
His name's Abdul Jamal Lewis Jones.
他很健康 他的妈妈爱他
He healthy. His mother Love him.
医院的饭太难吃了
The food in this hospital's nasty.
这不是
it's not from here.
那是哪来的?
Where it from?
我家附近的摊子
A little shop by my house where
我在那儿买有机食品
I get my organic food, so I don't have to eat that
所以不用去楼下吃那难吃的饭菜了
nasty mystery- meat stuff they got downstairs.
给我带点行不?我不喜欢水果 我喜欢麦当劳
Can you bring me something? I don't like fruit. I like McDonald's.
首先 我不吃麦当劳
First of all, I don't eat McDonald's.
其次 你也没必要吃麦当劳
Second of all, you don't need to be eating McDonald's, either.
不健康
it's not healthy.
我喜欢麦当劳 我们都喜欢麦当劳 对吧?
But I like McDonald's. We all like McDonald's, right?
# 我们也喜欢麦当劳
We like McDonald's, too, over here.
咱可不喜欢麦当劳
I don't like no damn McDonald's.
咱想试试看你的有机狗屎...
I want some of that organic shit like you got.
好吧... 告诉你们吧
Well, I tell you what,
当你出去以后 你和你的朋友们可以去麦当劳...
when you get up out of here, you go with all your little friends, and you go to McDonald's, and you get as much McDonald's as you want.
想吃多少麦当劳都行 但是现在... 我负责你的健康
But right now, you're gonna take care of your health.
你是个医生么?
Are you a doctor?
- 你是医生么? - 我是不是医生?
- Are you her doctor? - Am I a doctor?
- 对阿 - 我是个护士
- Yeah. - I am a nurse's aide. Nurse John John.
这很有趣么?
Oh, that's funny?
但你是男的阿
Well, you're a man.
- 你没见过男的护士么? - 没 没
- You've never seen a male nurse? - No.
见过但和你干的不一样
Not looking like you do.
我就是个男护士 我是护士约翰·麦克法登
I am a male nurse. I am Nurse John McFadden.
那么 你是不是进了产房 唰 就把婴儿从她的双腿间拽出来
So was you up in the room when she popped the baby out?
像这样 把手伸进她的
You was like, all up in between her...
乔安 你说得太恶心了
Joann, don't be nasty!
感觉怎样? 你喊了么?
How was it? Was he screaming?
非常疼
it hurt.
像你这么坚强也喊出来了?
Tough gal like you had to scream?
也没强到能生下一个宝宝也不觉得疼 真的很疼
Not so tough with a baby coming out of me. it hurt. And it burned.
- 你结婚了没? 你结婚了没? - 闭嘴吧!
- Are you married? - Shut up!
有女朋友没?
You got a girlfriend?
- 你问这有啥意义? 他又不会要你 - 你又怎么知道?
- Why you asking? He don't want you. - How would you know?
你就少发春十分钟吧?
Why don't you stop being a ho for 10 minutes?
- 我才没发春 - 这群人是怎么回事?
- oh - What's wrong with these people?
你不会想要她 对吧?
You don't want her, right?
我多想自己是那个盒子里的水果
I wish I was a cantaloupe in that cup.
想被他吃么?
So he could eat you?
好了 我该走了 我走了
Okay, no. I gotta go. I gotta go.
别那么着急走嘛! 没事 没事
No, that's all right. That's all right.
给我也来个吻行么 护士约翰?
Can I get a kiss, too, Nurse John?
- 午安 女士们 - 再见 护士约翰
- Good afternoon, ladies. - Bye, Nurse John.
- 谢谢了 护士约翰 - 再见 小护士约翰...
- Bye! - Good night, Nurse John John!
老天啊 阿珍珍和小约翰
Precious and John John
坐在树荫下
Sitting in a tree
搂搂抱抱好快乐
- F- U- C- K- l- N- G - Shut up! Y'all are nasty.
他说不定会来这里过夜
You think he's spending the night up in here?
你应该整本书都写护士约翰好了
Now she gonna write about Nurse John in her book!
亲爱的雨小姐
Dear Ms. Rain,
我坐在教室里那么多年 什么都没有学到
All the years I sit in class, I never Learned.
现在因为我爸爸 我又生了一个孩子
Now I got a baby again by my father.
我希望我能像其他女孩一样有男朋友
I wish I had a boyfriend Like other girls.
不能继续上课我很难受
Then I'll feel right that I have to quit school.
我爱我的孩子 但我也想上学
I Love my baby, but I want school, too.
社工问我愿不愿意把 小芒果和阿杜送人领养
Social worker ask me if I wanna give Little Mongo
我真想掐死她 她之前就没帮上过什么忙
and Abdul up for adoption. I could kill her.
现在她又想把我孩子抢走?
She never helped before. Now she wanna take my kids away?
如果她带走了阿杜 我就什么也没有了
If she takes Abdul, I won't have nothing no more."
亲爱的阿珍
Dear Precious,
我认为你首先应该要为自己负责
I think your first responsibility has to be to yourself.
如果你送走了阿杜 你或许一无所有
If you keep Abdul, you might have nothing.
你学会了读书写字 这就是一切
You're Learning to read and write. That's everything.
当你出了医院回到学校来时
You come back to school when you get out of the hospital.
你只有17岁
You're only 17.
这个真像一个超级大的安全套
This looks like a big ass condom.
你可真了解
Use that for Nurse John.
先别说那个 你的头发看上去一团糟
Not looking like that. Your hair looks a mess.
- 我送你台奔驰吧 - 闭嘴吧你
- I'm giving you banz. - Shut up!
- 我把你笔记拿来了 - 谢谢
- I got your journal. - Thank you.
- 怎么了? - 没啥
What's wrong? - Nothing.
- 你确定? - 当然 没事
Are you sure? - Yeah, I'm sure.
我也待烦了 该走了 拜
All right. I'm bored. I'm about to leave. Bye.
拜 图茜小姐
Bye, Ms. Toosie.
你的嘴巴可真脏
You got a nasty ass mouth.
你的脑袋可真脏
You got a nasty ass hat.
和那种贱女人混在一起可不好
That's what's wrong, you hanging out with bitches like that.
给你宝宝
Here's your baby.
说不定是你最后一次看他了
it's probably the last time you're gonna ever see him.
奶奶来看我 说
Grandmother come and visit and say,
只有狗生下孩子才会弃之不顾
"Only a dog would drop a baby and walk off.
连狗都不会
Not even a dog.
过了一会 又说连狗都不会
Say later, "Not even a dog.
我为你感到骄傲 你妈一点都比不上你
I'm proud of you. Ain't nothing like your mother.
当你父亲在虐待你时 你的奶奶又在哪里?
Where was your grandmother when your father was abusing you?
现在小芒果又在哪里?
Where is Little Mongo now?
在这种情况下 怎样做才对你最好?
What is going to be the best thing for you in this situation?
雨小姐 你问的问题好多
Ms. Rain, you ask too many questions.
有时我不禁的屏住了呼吸
Sometimes I wish I could stop breathing.
我只想做一个好妈妈
I just wanna be a good mother.
成为一个好妈妈或许意味着 让阿杜在一个更好的家庭长大
Being a good mother might mean Letting Abdul be raised
得到自己所需
by someone who's better able than you to meet his needs.
雨小姐 我就是阿杜最需要的
Ms. Rain, I is the best to meet my child's needs.
谁来帮你?
Who's gonna help you?
你该怎样养家?
How will you support yourself?
你该怎样继续学习读书写作?
How will you keep Learning to read and write?
社保就帮了我妈妈
The welfare helped Momma.
你也看到了社保有帮到你妈妈多少
You look and see how much welfare has helped your mom.
你可以继续你的正式课程
You could get your GED,
你可以上大学 你可以做任何事 阿珍
and go to college. You can do anything, Precious.
你回来了?
You back?
他名字叫啥? 我能抱抱么?
What's his name? Can I hold it?
好啊 阿珍
Hey, Precious.
嗨
Hey.
- 又生了个孩子? - 是个男孩
You had the baby? - A boy.
这么长时间你去哪儿了?
Where you been all this time?
让我看看
Let me see him.
我能抱抱么?
Can I hold him?
长得像他爸
He look like his daddy.
我给他取名叫阿杜
He named Abdul.
把身上那堆垃圾放下 给我弄杯喝的来
Put all this shit down and go get me something to drink.
你个婊子! 你操他妈的婊子!
You bitch!
- 疯了么 妈? - 觉得我疯了么?
- You fucking bitch! - You crazy, Momma?
婊子 我他妈...
Am I crazy? Bitch, if I was to...
你他妈的毁了我的生活
You ruined my fucking life!
你抢了我的男人! 和他的生了他妈的孩子
You done took my man, you had those fucking babies,
还他妈的没有补助
and you got me put off the welfare
都是因为你天杀的操他妈的这张蠢嘴
for running your goddamned stupid ass mouth!
我不蠢! 我也没有勾引你男人! 是你男人强奸我!
I ain't stupid and I didn't take your man. Your husband raped me!
什么人他妈的强奸你
Didn't no fucking body rape you!
少拿你他妈的脏手碰我!
Bitch, don't you put your fucking hands on me!
# 庆祝的时间到了
# 让我们齐聚一堂
# 分享我们洋溢的爱
# 让我们感受到彼此
# 佳节
# 爱在蔓延
# 我们带着爱意共享这特殊的日子
# 圣诞
# 主诞生的日子
# 多么神圣的日子
# 哦 神圣的日子
我能看看宝宝么?
Can I see the baby now?
# 神圣的节日
# 节日的庆典总在变化
# 那又将何
# 我们不能忘记我们因何而在此
# 原因自在 原因皆知
# 穿越过四季
# 我们的信仰 献给我们所敬仰
# 多么神圣的日子
# 节日的庆典总在变化
# 那又将何
# 我决不忘记我因何而在此
# 原因在此 穿越四季
# 我们的信仰 献给...
A... B... C... D... C... D... E... E... F... G... H... F... G... H...
l... J... K... l... m... n...
我买东西都买烦了
I'm tired of shopping.
是啊 因为做生意的都跟抢钱似的
Yes, because they all trying to take your money.
他们不...
They don't...
我去报警了
I'm calling the cops.
告诉我你在后面看到什么了!
Tell me what you see back there.
我能从雨小姐的表情看出来 我不会再无家可归了
I could tell by Ms. Rain's face I ain't gonna be homeless no more.
但我不知道最后我会落脚在何处
I just don't know where I'm gonna end up, though.
我等着
I'll hold.
我感到很对不起她
I feel bad for her.
她只是个教文法基础的老师 她不是社工
She just an ABC teacher. She ain't no social worker.
怎么回事?
What's going on?
但她全揽在自己肩上
But she all I could think of.
当其他人到的时候 告诉他们开始写作
Look, when the others get here, tell them to start writing.
你们之中谁最大 谁就先负责 好么!
And whichever one of you is older is in charge, okay?
坎翠拉 我知道你最大 过来
Consuelo, I know that's not you. Come here.
我现在不能留...
Ms. Rain, I can't stay. I'm serious. I've tried to talk...
坎翠拉 我不准你逃课 我现在不跟你争论这个
Consuelo, you're not leaving class and I'm not dealing with this right now.
把这钱拿上 去给阿珍买点穿的
Take this money. Go get something for Precious to wear.
快点 别忘了把找的钱给我
Quick. And bring back my change.
16岁大 还有一个三天大的婴儿
Sixteen years old. A three day old infant.
宝宝没有流血 我想那应该是阿珍的血
The baby not bleeding. I think this is Precious' blood.
那你为什么不一开始就告诉我呢?
Well, why didn't you tell me that before?
我会给你找到住的地方的
We'll find you a place to live.
乔安 你迟到了
Joann, you're late.
兰达 你想做老师啊
Rhonda, you ain't the teacher.
乔安 雨小姐今天要忙阿珍的事
Joann, Ms. Rain is busy with Precious today,
所以我就系老师 今天
so I am the teacher today.
好吧 为啥?
Okay. Why?
先坐吧
- Where's Precious? - Just sit. Pull out your notebook.
乔安 你想看给宝宝唱Rap什么效果么?
Joann, you wanna say one of your raps to the baby?
宝宝来这里干啥?
What's the baby doing here?
- 乔安不懂咯 - 让我看看
- Joann's gonna rap for you. - let me see.
她就是...
She all right. She's doing good.
宝宝怎么被一个沾血的蓝毯子包着?
Why is the baby wrapped up in a blood covered blanket?
乔安 有什么好笑的?
Joann, what's so funny?
不好笑! 但是到底发生什么了?
For real. What happened?
你不会想知道的
You don't wanna know is how it got on the blanket.
你知道你的问题所在么 乔安?
You know what your problem is, Joann?
就是你无法严肃处事
That you can't take anything serious enough.
- 我们又能期待你做出什么好事? - 好了 兰达
- Jermaine, me expect better from you. - Okay, Rhonda.
乔安 别再笑宝宝了
Joann, stop laughing at this baby.
拜托了
Queens.
等下再给你打回去
Let me call you back.
那告诉我 到底发生什么了?
Just tell me what happened!
- 这真的不好笑 - 宝宝被...
No, it's not funny.
乔安 一个粘血的宝宝有什么好笑的
But Joann, there's nothing funny about a baby with blood on it.
我认识一个人是一个议员
I got a West Indian friend who's a Council member.
来看看他能不能帮上忙 稍等下
Let me see what she can do. Hold on a second.
我在我们的书里找到了一课...
I found a lesson plan in our notebooks. We're gonna...
柯瑞丝·琼斯
Clarence Jones.
嗨 露西小姐 最近好么?
Hey, Ms. Lisa. How you been?
不太好
I don't know.
昨天我去看电影《蝴蝶》了 就是砣屎
I went to see that movie, Barfly, last night. Piece of shit.
- 就在我桌上 - 稍等一下好么
- I'm sorry. - it's on my desk. Can you hold?
你有些不对劲了 阿珍
Something's wrong with you, Precious.
宝宝身上都臭了
This baby stink.
我们有没有尿布可换 抱着孩子坐下吧
Well, we don't have a Pamper, so have a seat with the baby.
- 我就是坐着阿 - 请坐自己位置上
- I am sitting. - in your seat, please.
第一件事...
The first thing is shut the bumba.. ros... clot...
雨小姐? 你为什么让兰达教课
Ms. Rain, why did you let Rhonda teach the class?
她自己英语都说不好
She don't even know how to speak English.
就让兰达先管吧
Let Rhonda take over.
他妈的什么是"ros clot"
Shut the bumba ros clot up. What the fuck is a "ros clot"?
是 布兰迪 还在么? 社保号的最后四位?
Yeah, Brenda, you there? The last four of the Social are...
2 4 2 1
2- 4 2- 1 .
- 丽塔 - 我就是想知道
- Rita? - I just wanna know how to spell "Aquarius."
有人知道"Aquarius（宝瓶座）"怎么拼?
Anybody know how to spell "Aquarius"?
那你会不会拼"boy（男孩）"
it's A- Q- U- A- R- l- U- S. A- Q- U- A- R- I- U- S Can you spell "boy" then?
那你会不会拼 "slut(贱人)"呐
Can you spell "slut" then?
咱们一个一个来
Let's explore that.
想拼出 婊子坎翠拉 我先给你们第一个字母
You wanna spell "slut," Consuelo, I'll give you the first letter.
那你会不会拼"非法移民"呢?
Can you spell "illegal immigrant," then?
太好了 谢谢你
Great, thank you.
你能用 "sult" 造句吗?
Can you please use "slut" in a sentence?
坎翠拉是个贱人
Consuelo is a slut...
- 你才是在用XX的人好不好 - 乔安不是婊子
- You the one who's the ho up in here... - Joann is not a slut.
棒极了
Perfect. You get a gold star.
但是她知道她喜欢那样
But you know she likes that.
她就是没有安全感罢了
Well, she's just insecure.
- 你这样认为? - 没错
- You think? - Yeah.
- 但是挺好的 - 是挺好 你吃饱了么? - 恩
- That chicken was good. - Really good. Did you have enough? There ain't more, is there?
- 还有么? - 有阿
- is there more? - Yeah.
也许等一会儿吧 现在先不
Maybe later. Not now.
我不想让你觉得我很贪婪
I don't want you to think I'm greedy.
你一点也不贪婪 你要是还饿 就多吃点呗
You're not greedy. lf you're hungry, let's get you some more.
我想我该减下一点体重了
I guess I kind of eat too much sometimes, though.
不 没必要
No, you don't.
是你来了么?
- Blue, is that you? - Not always.
你在这里干什么?
What are you doing here?
我住在这儿呗 你怎么不告诉我?
I live here. Why didn't you tell me?
- 宝贝儿 - 这位是...?
- Hey, sweetie. - is this... is this...
这位是卡瑟琳 阿珍
This is Katherine, Precious.
- 你还好么? - 终于见到你了真高兴
- Are you okay? - it's so nice to meet you, finally.
哦 我的天 她们原来是女同性恋
Oh, my God. These straight- up lesbians.
- 这位是阿杜 - 太漂亮了 他看上去就像你一样
- This is Abdul. - He's gorgeous. He looks just like you.
- 阿珍 我能抱抱么? - 你知道怎么抱么?
- Precious, can I hold him? - You know how to?
但她们是那么好心 让我在找到安定的地方前
They still nice enough to let us stay in their home
住在她们家里
until I get situated, though.
- 还挺沉! 我的天 - 真是...
- He's heavy. Oh, my God! - You wanna hold him?
我猜这就是电视中的那些人 过圣诞节时的感觉吧
I guess this is how the peoples on TV feel at Christmastime.
- 别掉了 - 哦 拜托 我对小孩儿当然小心了
- Don't drop him. - Come on. I only work with children.
我还记得
You know how you are. I saw you...
你装饰圣诞树的时候 什么都掉地上
When we were putting up the tree, you dropped half the top of it.
她们对我和阿杜那么的好
They're so nice to me and Abdul.
小心点 两只手都用上
- Be careful. Hold him with both hands. - Please.
小阿杜
Oh, Abdul.
圣诞快乐 阿珍
Merry Christmas, Precious.
谢谢你
Thank you.
为什么几乎不认识我的人
Why peoples that barely know me
待我都比我爸爸我妈妈要好?
should be nicer to me than my mother and my father?
- 我感觉到温暖 - 你把猫关起来了么?
- I felt warm.
- 什么?! - 我就是...
- What? - I'm just...
我就是担心宝宝 猫还在楼上
I'm just concerned about the baby and the cats upstairs.
- 没事的 - 好吧
- They're fine. - OK
奶奶害怕妈妈
Grandmother's scared of Momma.
这知道这就是她不让我和她住一起的原因
I know that's why she ain't Letting me stay with her.
如果麦当劳...
lf Ronald McDonald were running things...
雨小姐说什么都不要怕
Ms. Rain say don't be afraid of nothing.
我打赌她不会害怕我妈妈
I bet she ain't scared of Momma.
难道你不会心生疑惑么?
Wouldn't you be a little bit suspicious?
那你写成书吧
Just write the book.
- 那谁来看呢? - 你不写也没人看啊
- Well, who's gonna read it? - Nobody, if you don't write it.
知道么 阿珍天天都写作
You know, Precious writes every day. You should try it.
是么? 你都写些什么呢 阿珍?
is that right? What do you write about, Precious?
就是
Stuff.
我的生活 阿杜...
My life. Abdul.
你们怎么会都不喜欢麦当劳呢?
How come y'all don't like McDonald's?
卡瑟琳只是做些比较...
Katherine was just drawing a comparison
这样她的观点可以更容易被理解...
so that her point could be more easily understood. Yes.
她们说话就像我不看的电视频道
They talk Like TV channels I don't watch.
- 谁会看呢? - 比如 克力顿大叔
My Uncle Clayton.
我很高兴阿杜也能听着
I'm glad Abdul here to Listen in on them, though,
因为我知道她们很聪明
'cause I know they're smart. Before he got saved,
他吸起烟来就像个烟囱 喝起酒来像条鱼
he used to smoke like a chimney and drink like a fish.
她们说的我一个字都听不懂
I don't understand a word they're saying.
明白么?
You understand?
你们都看歌剧么?
Y'all be watching Oprah?
不 其实我不看 你知道我下班回家都几点了?
No. I don't, actually. You know what time I get home from work.
- 我看 - 妈妈说同性恋都是坏人
- I watch it. - Momma say homos is bad peoples.
那你应该写作啊
you should write
但是妈妈 同性恋不是对我暴力的人
But Momma, homos not ones who raped me.
为什么你是?
And what do that make you?
同性恋让我学到了我在学校 那么多年没有学到的东西
Homos not ones who let me sit in class all them years and never Learn nothing.
同性恋也不是黑人区卖毒品的那些
The homos not ones who sell crack to peoples in Harlem.
- 我从没见过 告诉她!
- ...that I have ever seen. Tell her! - That doesn't work.
歌剧里是怎样描述这些的?
I wonder what Oprah got to say about that.
是雨小姐将粉笔递在我手中
Ms. Rain is the one who put the chalk in my hand,
让我成为字母表的女王
made me queen of the ABC's.
自从我在一间中转房落脚后
After I settled at the halfway house,
我开始尽我的努力学习 记忆
I worked my hardest to memorize Letter sounds,
写笔记 读各种书
writing in the journal, and reading smaller and fatter books.
后来我发现 市长办公室...
Then I found out the Mayor's office
给我颁发了文明进步奖 还有奖金支票
give me a Literacy award and a check for progress.
1, 2, 3.
One, two, three.
派对开始了
The party is on.
约翰
Go, Joann!
每个人都来了 护士约翰... 所有的工作人员都来了
Let me see what you got! Everybody come. Nurse John, Cornrows, all the staff was out there.
连卡瑟琳都来了
Even Ms. Katherine showed up.
阿珍!
Precious.
怎么了?
What's up?
让我看一下?
What's that?
这看上去像啥?
What does it look like?
就个塑料苹果呗
Plastic stupid apple.
给你点东西
A little something for you.
- 是给我的钱么? - 你怎么那么贪呢
- is there more money in it? - You're so greedy.
那个...那两位是谁?
Yo, who's that?
咋了?
What?
- 怎么啦?! - 过来!
- What? - Come on.
阿珍 你要带我去哪儿?
Precious, where are you taking me?
那我该怎么办 事儿妈? 没错 先等下
What am I supposed to do, diva? Yeah? Wait a minute.
先别挂 姑娘 什么事 阿...
Hold on, girl. Yeah...
我妈昨晚打电话给我
My mom called last night.
而...我们没怎么有来往
And we don't really have a relationship.
我们不谈话 她对我是...
We don't talk, because she really has a problem with...
有些人就像一盏明灯照亮周围的人
Some folks got a light around them that shine for other peoples.
有些人曾经就像生活在隧道里
I think maybe some of them was in tunnels,
而那隧道 唯一的光亮就是
and in that tunnel, maybe the only Light they had
内心的光亮
was inside of them.
我想过你要多坚强来承受这一切
Then I thought about how strong you've had to be.
而然后 即使在逃离了隧道很久之后...
And then, even Long after they escaped that tunnel...
- 我来打扫 - 好吧
- I'll help you clean up. - Okay.
内心的光亮依然照耀着别人
...they still be shining for everybody else.
雨小姐对我来说就是这样
That's Ms. Rain to me.
在我读的这本书里 有一个女人逃到了中转房
In a book I read, this Lady escaped to a halfway house.
当她在那里时
And when she was there,
她问那里的人 中转房是什么意思
she asked the people there what a halfway house was.
他们告诉他 这就是你过去 的生活和你想要的生活的中转站
They told her it was halfway between her old life and where she wanna be.
感觉挺好的
That's kind of nice.
这也意味着我不能一辈子待在这里
That also mean I can't stay here forever.
还有很长的路要走
There's still a way to go.
要是我有了自己的公寓该多好
It'd be something to get my own apartment.
阿杜九个月大了 差不多能走路了 他也很聪明
Abdul nine months and almost walking. He's smart, too.
从他出生的那天起我就读书给他听
I've been reading to him since the day he was born.
他还不会说话 但他已经懂一些了
He's barely talking, but he's already counting.
妈妈 爸爸
Momma, Daddy,
林克斯大道444号的日子 在我看来已经是过去的噩梦了
444 Lenox all seem Like some old, bad dream.
我真希望一切是从这里开始 但还是和阿杜在一起
I wish I could've just started out here, but still with Abdul.
还有小芒果 我要把小芒果带回来
I'm gonna get Mongo, too. I gotta get Mongo back.
嗨 汤森夫人
Hey, Miss Cassidy.
嗨 阿珍 下面有人在等你
Hey, Precious, somebody downstairs for you.
- 是谁? - 我不知道是谁
- Who is it? - I didn't ask who it was.
用我帮你看孩子么?
You want me to watch the baby?
不用了 我正好也要下去
No, I gotta go down and get him anyway.
你爸死了
Your daddy dead.
就说这?
That's all?
他得了爱滋
He had that AlDS virus.
阿珍!
Precious
阿珍 你听到我跟你说话了么?
Precious, do you hear me talking to you?
你听到我说什么了么?
Did you hear what I said?
你得了么?
You got it?
得啥?
Got what?
- 艾滋病 - 没
- The AlDS virus. - No.
你怎么知道?
How do you know?
我们从没做过肛交的 所以我知道
We never did it up in the ass, so I know.
你最好去看看医生 妈
You better get to a doctor, Mom.
你回家不?
You coming home?
哟 阿珍!
Yo, Precious!
莉塔
Rita,
如果一个作者写一个人是
what do I mean when I say the author describes her protagonist's
不知天高地厚 是什么意思
circumstances as "unrelenting"?
我不知道 不知道
I don't know. I don't know.
比方说丽塔 朝一个方向走路
it's like, say, like if Rita, she tries to do something,
该停的时候 又接着走
and she's going and she's going, and me, I try to stop her
她不停 又接着走
and she no stop, she keep on going.
不管周围 那样
Relentless- un.
那稍后见 再见
I'll see you tonight. Bye.
为什么是我?
来一下
Come with me.
阿珍?
Precious?
抱歉?
Excuse me?
护士说我HIV阳性
Nurse say I'm HlV positive.
我今天什么都不想写
I don't got nothing to write today.
孩子们还好么?
is your baby okay?
没事 只要我不用母乳喂他们的话
He all right. I just got to stop breastfeeding him.
还记得曾经有一次你告诉我...
Remember, you once told me
你还没有好好的和他讲过故事
you never really got to tell your story.
- 写下来 - 操你!
- Write. - Fuck you!
我所经历的你知道个屁!
You know nothing of what I've been through.
我从没有过男朋友
I don't never had no boyfriend.
我爸爸说他想娶我
My daddy said he gonna marry me.
为什么呢? 因为他想合法操我!
How he gonna do that? it would fucking be illegal!
写
Write.
我受够了 雨小姐
I'm tired, Ms. Rain.
如果不想为自己写 那为爱你的人写
lf not for yourself, then for the people who love you.
没人爱我
Nobody loves me.
人们爱你 阿珍
People do love you, Precious.
请你别骗我了 雨小姐
Please don't lie to me, Ms. Rain.
爱从来没为我带来什么好处
Love ain't done nothing for me.
爱 打我 强奸我
Love beat me, raped me,
称我为野兽 让我觉得自己一无是处 让我得病
called me an animal, make me feel worthless. Make me sick.
那不是爱 阿珍
That wasn't love, Precious.
你的宝宝爱你
Your baby loves you.
我爱你
I love you.
写
Write.
你在想些什么呢?
What are you thinking?
你从没跟我说过 你和你妈妈的关系
You never told me about your relationship with your mother.
我是没说过 是吧?
I didn't, did l?
真的 我来这里是帮助你
Really, I'm here to help you.
你可以和我谈 这里很安全
You can talk to me. This is a safe environment.
你说得没错
You're right.
要不然谈谈你爸爸也可以
We could talk about your daddy instead.
我们可以谈谈我妈妈 我爸爸 我姨妈...
We could talk about my mother, my father,
我姐姐和我哥哥 但这都不会帮到你
my aunts or my sister or my brother, but none of it's gonna help you.
你一点都不喜欢我
You don't even like me.
我们不是已经在这房间里
Have we not been in this room together
相处有一年时间 讨论你的生活么?
for, like, a year, discussing your life?
就是说讨论了我的生活 我们就可以互相喜欢了么?
Does that mean we like each other, because we discuss my life?
我不能替你说 我只能说我自己的想法 而我是喜欢你的
I can't speak for you. I can only speak for me, and I do like you. I do.
那 你是意大利人
So, are you Italian, or...
算是什么人种呢?
What color are you, anyway?
算是某种黑人还是西班牙人?
Are you some type of black or Spanish?
你觉得我算什么人种呢?
What color do you think I am?
现在我挺想知道的 你觉得我是什么人种呢?
No, I'd like to know. What color do you think I am?
我喉咙干了
My throat is dry.
- 你喉咙干了? - 这里挺热的
- Your throat is dry? - it's really hot in here.
这儿是挺热的
it is kind of hot in here.
我去买瓶汽水 你要什么?
I'm gonna go get a soda. What do you want?
我也要汽水就行
Soda sounds fine.
好的
All right.
谢谢你
Thank you.
不客气
No problem.
那么 我必须跟你谈谈你妈妈的事
So, I have to talk to you about your mother,
我不知道你做何感想 但是
and I don't know how you're gonna feel about this,
她说她想看看你...
but she says she wants to see you
她想和你还有孙子重聚
and she wants to be reunited with you and her grandchildren.
她想来和你会面谈谈
She wants to come and have a session here with you.
你怎么跟她说的?
What did you tell her?
我说我会转告给你的
I said I had to speak to you about it.
你来决定
it's up to you.
我不知道 我也从没有想过
I don't know. I never thought about it before.
怀斯小姐说没什么比的上HIV病毒
Ms. Weiss said in that flee I got HIV.
她说我会因此而死
She said I was supposed to die from it.
我不担心我死
I ain't worried about dying.
我担心怎样才能养大我的孩子
Shit, I gotta worry about how I'm supposed to raise these kids.
我刚写的是关于...
I was just writing, like, about...
我想开这么一个诊所
I wanna open up this clinic
关注母亲和孩子...
about, like, mothers and their children.
就是有病或者之类的...
You know, just, if they're sick or something like that.
我总是想这么做 帮助邻里 因为我知道我妈妈
I always wanted to do that, give back to the community.
一定会为我感到骄傲 还有我的孩子也是
Because I know my mom would be proud of me if I did that, and my children, too.
我想我的孩子为妈妈感到骄傲 是吧?
I want my children to be proud of their mother, you know?
- 这就是我想做的 所以... - 就这样 挺好的
- That's always what I wanted to do, so... - That's good. That's really nice.
我希望大家都能听一下 我是想说一下怎么回事
I don't really want to read the whole thing, I kind of just wanna say what it's about.
好的... 救助中心去谈话的事
Okay, the counselors at Advancement House,
是因为我爸爸和妈妈 对吧?
they were quizzing me about my mother and my father, right?
其实不是关于他们的
But it's not really about them.
他们想让我在那里工作
They're trying to get me to do workfare.
- 他们想让我做陪护员 - 你怎么知道的?
- They want me to be a home attendant. - How do you know?
因为我在那儿偷了我的档案
Because I stole my file and I read it.
他们想让我做的就是工作
All they want me to do is work.
我是想要工作 但我不想要赚得不够养活自己的工作
Now, I do wanna work, but not for no welfare check. What kind of sense that make,
这样做到底意义何在? 像阿珍这样高中没毕业就被退学
for somebody like Precious to quit school before she got her GED
然后去不知道什么地方给白人老人干活?
and go work for some old white people somewhere?
她什么坏事也没做 没理由被害得被困在这上面
She ain't never gonna be nothing if she gets stuck in some shit like that.
兰达曾经当过陪护员
Rhonda used to home attend.
她去过布利莱顿海滩
She used to have to go all the way out to Brighton Beach.
好的 兰达曾经作陪护整天整夜
Yeah, okay, Rhonda would be working there all day and night.
随时摇铃呼唤 是吧?
She'd be on call, right?
赚时薪6.37美元 按照八小时工作制
She made $6.37 an hour, but for only eight hours.
所以一天是50.96美元
That equal out to $50.96.
但这可没多少钱
But that's not a whole lot of money,
因为事实 她工作24小时
especially 'cause, for real, she there for 24 hours.
所以... 50.96除以24
So, $50.96 divided by 24 is $2.1 2 an hour.
那就是时薪2,06美元 这可没多少钱
That's not a lot of money.
她说那个老贱人会摇铃铛 货真价实的铃铛
She said that old bitch would ring a bell, like, a real life, actual bell
如果她半夜想要她干点啥
when she wanted something from her in the middle of the night.
- 谁想干那破事 - 兰达 是真的么 兰达?
- You don't want to do that shit. - Rhonda, is that true? Rhonda!
陪护员一天要工作6天
Them home attendants be working for, like, six days a week.
那我只能在周日见阿杜了 而且还不能上课了?
I'd only see Abdul on Sunday. Plus, I'd have to leave class.
那么 那不可行 你不能离开课堂
Well, that's not an option. You're not leaving class.
另外 下次还要去讨论"insect(虫子)"问题
Plus, I'm gonna start going to insect survivor meetings.
那是"incest"(乱伦)
it's "incest."
- 我不是那么说的么? - 不是 你说的是insect
- That ain't what I said? - No, you said "insect."
有啥区别?
What's the difference?
一个是指你家庭内问题
Well, one's where your family molests you,
另一个是指虫子 昆虫
the other's like a roach or bugs.
- 哦 你现在是科学家了? - 我就是说一下吗
- So, you a scientist now? - I'm just saying.
没事 挺好 谢谢你
No, that's cool. Thank you. Thank you.
当知道爸死了时 是一种既难过又奇怪的感觉
It was hard telling them strangers there what my father did.
有时候感觉很好
Sometimes it felt good.
上一周雨小姐让我们写自己梦想的样子
Last week, Ms. Rain asked us to write down what we wanna be like.
我写的是 我想要非常苗条
I wrote that I be real skinny,
黑皮肤 长头发
with Light skin and Long hair.
路易桑·赫卢威?
Loretta Holloway?
马上就到
Go on back there.
她回写道 我现在就很漂亮
She read it and said I'm beautiful like I am.
这儿也没人和我一起玩
But, there's no kids back there for me to play with.
闭嘴好好坐着
Just shut up and sit there, then.
我去和那娘们谈谈话 免得我们饭钱给断了
Gonna talk to this lady before my shit gets cut off.
不知怎的...
But somehow,
现在... 我不知道为什么 但是...
right now... And I don't know why, but...
我想她说得没错
I think she right.
给你
Here.
柯瑞丝·琼斯!
Clarence Jones?
我想她说得没错
I think she right.
好的 琼斯女士
Okay, Mrs. Johnston,
我们来谈谈虐待(abuse也指'滥用')问题
let's talk about the abuse.
我们家可没有毒品 我不来那个
There were no drugs in my house.
我们家没毒品 阿珍知道...
I didn't play that. There weren't no drugs in my house. Precious knew I would whup her ass
如果她带毒品回家 我让她吃不了兜着走
if she gonna bring some drugs up in my house.
你知道我指的什么
You know what I'm talking about.
我想特指的是身体上的 性行为上的虐待
I'm referring to specific sexual and physical acts
涉及到阿珍的
involving Precious.
你为啥那么说?
Why you ain't say that?
没错 就是
Yes, that.
你...你想知道什么?
What do you wanna know?
如阿珍的档案所写 她已经生过两个孩子
According to Precious' files, she has now had two children
父亲是 赖特·卡尔·温伍德·琼斯...
by your boyfriend. the late Carl Kenwood Jones,
同时也是阿珍的生父?
who was also her father.
- 是的 - 这是没错的?
- Yeah. - This is accurate?
是的 怀斯小姐
Yes, Ms. Weiss.
而你来这里的原因 是因为你打电话到这个办公室
I need to know why you're here. You've been calling this office
说想要和阿珍重聚 还有你的孙子
saying you want to be reunited with Precious and your grandchild.
我真的需要知道 那个家里 到底发生了什么?
Now, I really need to know what's gone on in that home.
怀斯小姐 我明白你想讨论什么 但是...
Ms. Weiss, I understand we need to discuss it,
我想告诉你 你说我打电话到这里
but I'm just telling you.
说想再见到阿珍和孙子
You said I've been calling here and I've been wanting to see Precious and my grandson.
这太逑对了 我就是想见 他们就是属于我的 好么
You're goddamn right I wanna see them. Because they belong to me. Okay?
曾经有那么一段时间 阿珍什么都不缺
Now, there was a time Precious had everything,
这你就不知道
and I done told her that.
而我和卡尔 我们爱阿珍
And me and Carl, we loved Precious. And you need to know that.
这你应该知道 我们爱阿珍 我们也有过梦想
We loved Precious and we had dreams.
阿珍出生正好是... 维丝大妈儿子死的时候
Precious was born around the same time Ms. West's son got killed.
是夏天 她是生在... 在夏天
The summertime. She was born in the summertime.
还记得么 记得...?
Remember? Remember that?
我十一月生的
I was born in November.
十一月...
November.
没错... 说得没错...
Yeah, that's right.
蛇蝎心肠的孩子
My Scorpio child.
你知道么...
You know...
蛇蝎心肠 可是... 会很狡猾的
Scorpios, they can be tricky.
我不是说...我不是说她撒谎了
And, I'm not saying that they lie. I'm not saying that.
我没有说 但你要注意着点
But you just gotta watch them.
我们能不能谈谈
Can we talk about the actual acts
确切发生的事情和性虐待
of physical and sexual abuse
发生在你家里的
that occurred in your household?
最早是从什么时候开始?
When it first began,
在哪里发生的? 你作何反应?
where it happened and how did you respond?
阿珍还是个小女孩时
Precious was a little girl.
试试看想起当时她有多大?
Try and remember how old you think she was.
她当时3岁
She was three.
我当时... 用奶瓶喂她
And I had been giving her the bottle
而奶子给卡尔吃
and I was giving Carl the tit tie
因为我乳房的奶都没了
because my milk hadn't dried up in my breasts
不过不是因为她 是因为卡尔
but not from her, but because Carl was...
因为卡尔喝我的奶
Because Carl was sucking on them
所以我的奶水就不够了
and that's what kept my milk in my breasts.
而我以为这都是为了卫生
And I thought that that was for hygiene.
我做的都是我妈妈教给我的...
I did what my mother told me
做了对我孩子该做的 这就是我做的
that I was supposed to do with my child, so that's what I did.
而你就那么坐在那里 想来审判我
And you're sitting up there and you're trying to judge me...
我不是想审判你 但是如果你想申请补助的话
I'm not judging you, but you're asking me for money
你想和你的孙子重聚的话
and you're asking me to be reunited with your grandson.
但是 怀斯小姐 我不想让你用那种眼神看着我
But, Ms. Weiss, I don't like you looking at me like that.
你使唤这个婊子看着我... 好像看着什么操他妈的怪物
You got this bitch looking at me like I'm some kind of fucking monster.
在我的办公室不允许这么说话 好么?
We don't talk like this in my office, okay?
我不想他和她做爱 很恶心
I didn't want her sucking behind him, because that was nasty.
而事情就是那么... 事情就是很肮脏 怀斯小姐
And things that he was... it was just nasty, Ms. Weiss.
我...我...
I... I...
我有男人 我有孩子
I had a man, and I have a child
我两个都要照顾 是吧?
and I had to take care of both of them. Okay?
难道我想卡尔... 动我的孩子?
Did I want Carl to touch my baby?
当孩子躺在我身边时
Because I would lay my baby.
就躺在我身边的枕头上
I would lay her on the side of me, on this pillow
是个... 那是个粉红的小枕头
and it was pink
白色的花边 还写着她的名字
and it had this little white writing on it
就是阿珍
and it had her name, because she was precious.
我让我的宝贝睡这个枕头
And I would lay my baby on that pillow
而卡尔躺在床的另一边
and Carl would be laying on the other side
然后 我们开始...开始 做的时候
and then we would... We would start doing it
他摸了过来
and he reached over
他动了我的宝宝
and he touched my baby.
然后我质问他
And I asked him,
我说 卡尔 你干什么呢?
I said, "Carl, what are you doing?"
他跟我说
And he told me to shut...
闭上你的臭嘴 这是为了她好
To shut my fat ass up, and it was good for her.
- 那你接下来怎么做了呢? - 我闭上了我的臭嘴啊
- And what did you do then? - I shut my fat ass up.
我不想你坐在那里审判我 怀斯小姐
And I don't want you to sit there and judge me, Ms. Weiss.
你闭了嘴 你就让他虐待你的女儿
You shut up and you let him abuse your daughter?
我不想他虐待我的女儿
I did not want him to abuse my daughter.
- 我不想他虐待我的女儿 - 但是你允许了
- I did not want him to hurt her. - But you allowed him
让他那样做
to hurt her.
我不想让他对她做任何事 我想他和我做爱
I did not want him to do nothing to her. I wanted him to make love to me.
那是我的男人 那是我的男人
That was my man. That was my fucking man.
他是我的男人 但他想要我的女儿
That was my man and he wanted my daughter.
这就是我之所以恨她
And that's why I hated her.
因为我的男人应该爱我
Because my man, who was supposed to be loving me,
应该和我做爱
who was supposed to be making love to me,
却和我的孩子做爱 而她导致他离开
was fucking my baby.
是她导致他不回家
She made him leave. She made him go away.
那到底是谁的错呢?
So, whose fault was it, then?
那是这个贱人的错! 因为她让我的男人占有她
it's this bitch's fault because she let my man have her
但她啥也没有做! 她没有尖叫 她什么也没有做!
and she didn't say nothing. She didn't scream. She didn't do nothing.
那么 她给你说的那么多我怎么对待她
So, those things she told you I did to her,
那谁...谁 来爱我呢?
who else was gonna love me?
你以为你有学历 你他妈的就什么东西都懂?
Since you got your degree and you know every fucking thing?
谁又来爱我? 谁来让我觉得好受?
who was gonna love me, who was gonna make me feel good?
谁又能抚摸我 让我快乐 当夜晚到来的时候?
Who was gonna touch me and make me feel good late at night?
她使得他一去不回
And she made him go away,
所以 当你坐在那里 在你的笔记本上写下这纪录时
so... When you sit there and you write them fucking notes on your pad
写你觉得我怎么样 我都做过什么 这一切
about who you think I am, and why I did it, all of that.
因为我也一无所有
Because I didn't have nobody.
那些人... 来自...
The people from
一对一教学的那些
Each One Teach One,
他们曾... 他们告诉我...
they had... They called me
他们告诉我我的孩子在写诗
and they told me that my baby was writing poems.
事实上...知道么? 我拿来了...
in fact, you know what, I got...
等一下...
Wait a minute.
对不起 对不起
I'm sorry.
怀斯小姐 我不想要支票
I'm sorry. And, Ms. Weiss, I don't want no checks.
我不想要钱 拜托了 我很抱歉
I don't need no more money. Please. I'm so sorry.
我又做了一次那个测试
I took that TABE test again.
怎么样?
And what happened?
我得了7.8分
I scored a 7.8.
上一次是2.8分
Last time it was 2.8.
按照那个测试
According to that test,
我读书是7- 8年级的水平了
I'm reading at a seventh and eighth- grade level.
接下来我要读高中 再接下来读大学
Next year, high school. After that, college.
但我也喜欢你
Well, I like you, too.
但你不能解决我的事
But you can't handle me.
这些都不是你的能力范围
You can't handle none of this.
知道么 直到今天我才知道你的过去
You know, I never knew what you was until this day.
在你做的那一切之后
Not even after all them things you did.
或许是我太傻 也许是我就是不想要
Maybe I was too stupid, or maybe I just didn't want to.
你再也别想见到我了
You ain't gonna see me no more.
再见
Bye!
我不想他伤害我的孩子
I didn't want him to hurt my baby.
拜托 天啊 我从来没想伤害我的孩子
Please, God, I didn't want him to hurt my baby.
怀斯小姐 我不想他伤害我的孩子
Ms. Weiss, I didn't want him to hurt my baby.
我跟他说了
I would say to him, I would say...
我说 卡尔 你在干什么? 你在干什么 你在干什么?
"Carl, what are you doing? What are you doing? What are you doing?"
你能让她回来么?
Can you go get her back?
你能做到的 因为这是你的工作
You can do that, because that's what you do.
这是你的工作
That's what you do.
我需要你去 把我的孩子带回来
I need you to go and I need you to get my baby back.
你告诉我 我可以来这里 你...可以...
You told me that I could come in here and you could get...
让阿珍和我谈
You could get Precious to say...
怀斯小姐 怀斯小姐
Ms. Weiss? Ms. Weiss? Ms. Weiss?
# 花了那么久才找到此处
# 花了那么久才得到快乐
# 花了那么久才认清你的脸庞
# 花了那么久四处追寻
# 花了那么久才找到此处
# 花了那么久才得到快乐
# 花了那么久才认清你的脸庞
# 花了那么久四处追寻
# 美事得来皆不易
# 皆不可急求
# 急促得来的爱
# 都将难以持久
# 所以花了那么 那么多年期遇
# 直到我们在一起前
# 我都是不完整的